<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://annyg.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://annyg.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-04-22T10:08:47+00:00</updated><id>https://annyg.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Portfolio for ANYthings. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">News – Publication examining persisting symptoms after SARS-CoV-2 infection</title><link href="https://annyg.github.io/blog/2024/publication_ijid-longcovid/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="News – Publication examining persisting symptoms after SARS-CoV-2 infection"/><published>2024-10-15T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-15T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annyg.github.io/blog/2024/publication_ijid-longcovid</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annyg.github.io/blog/2024/publication_ijid-longcovid/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="news">News</h3> <p>I am thrilled to announce the publication of our latest research paper in our large Norwegian COVID-19 Cohort Study with more than 160 000 study participants. This extensive study has allowed us to delve deeper into the long-term effects of COVID-19, a topic that is still largely undefined due to a lack of large-scale studies.</p> <p>Our research focused on the persistent symptoms experienced by COVID-19 patients, even up to 22 months after their initial SARS-CoV-2 test. We found that memory and concentration problems were reported more frequently by those who tested positive, even when accounting for symptoms present before the onset of COVID-19. Other persistent symptoms included fatigue, dyspnoea, anosmia, and dysgeusia.</p> <p>These findings underscore the long-term cognitive and somatic impacts of COVID-19, and the importance of ongoing support and care for those affected. We hope that our research will contribute to a better understanding of the long-term effects of COVID-19 and help inform future healthcare strategies.</p> <p>The paper is published in <a href="https://www.ijidonline.com/article/S1201-9712(24)00334-5/fulltext">International Journal of Infectious Diseases</a>.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/publication_preview/persisting_symptoms-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/publication_preview/persisting_symptoms-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/publication_preview/persisting_symptoms-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/publication_preview/persisting_symptoms.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure from the paper showing the frequencies (moving average and 95% confidence intervals) of symptoms reported before, during and after a positive or negative SARS-CoV-2 test. </div> <h4 id="abstract">Abstract</h4> <p><strong>Background</strong> There is a lack of large studies on long-COVID symptoms with symptoms measurements before the onset of COVID-19. Therefore, long-COVID is still poorly defined.</p> <p><strong>Methods</strong> The Norwegian COVID-19 Cohort Study is a population-based, open cohort of adult participants (aged 18-96 years) from Norway. From March 27, 2020, participants were recruited through social media, invitations, and nationwide media coverage. Fourteen somatic and cognitive symptoms were assessed at baseline and four follow-ups for up to 22 months. SARS-CoV-2 test status was obtained from a mandatory national registry or from self-report.</p> <p><strong>Findings</strong> After follow-up, 15 737 participants had a SARS-CoV-2-positive test, 67 305 a negative test, and 37 563 were still untested. Persistent symptoms reported more frequently by positive compared with negative participants one month after infection, were memory problems (3-6 months: adjusted odds ratio (aOR) = 6.8, CI = 5.7-8.1; &gt;18 months: aOR = 9.4, CI = 4.1-22), and concentration problems (3-6 months: aOR = 4.1, CI = 3.5-4.7; &gt;18 months: aOR = 4.4, CI = 2.0-9.7) as well fatigue, dyspnoea, anosmia and dysgeusia.</p> <p><strong>Interpretation</strong> COVID-19 was associated with cognitive symptoms, anosmia, dysgeusia, dyspnoea and fatigue as well as worsening of overall health up to 22 months after a SARS-CoV-2 test, even when correcting for symptoms before the onset of COVID-19.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news"/><category term="publication"/><category term="publication"/><category term="ijid"/><category term="ncc"/><category term="covid19"/><category term="cognition"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Persisting symptoms after SARS-CoV-2 infection published in International Journal of Infectious Diseases]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">News – Publication examining cognitive deficits after SARS-CoV-2 infection</title><link href="https://annyg.github.io/blog/2024/publication_bbi-health_brief/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="News – Publication examining cognitive deficits after SARS-CoV-2 infection"/><published>2024-09-10T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-10T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annyg.github.io/blog/2024/publication_bbi-health_brief</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annyg.github.io/blog/2024/publication_bbi-health_brief/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="news">News</h3> <p>I am excited to share our study investigating the impact of SARS-CoV-2 infections on executive functioning in a large cohort of 8000 participants. The study is published in <a href="https://www-sciencedirect-com.ezproxy.uio.no/science/article/pii/S2666354624001352">Brain, Behavior, &amp; Immunity - Health</a>.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/publication_preview/brief_a_freq_figure_v1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/publication_preview/brief_a_freq_figure_v1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/publication_preview/brief_a_freq_figure_v1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/publication_preview/brief_a_freq_figure_v1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure from the paper showing the proportion of participants scoring above the clinical cut-offs on BRIEF-A. </div> <p>This study is a part of a <a href="https://www-sciencedirect-com.ezproxy.uio.no/science/article/pii/S1551714422002816">PhD project</a>, where we examine the effect of cognitive rehabilitation for long-COVID.</p> <h4 id="abstract">Abstract</h4> <p><strong>Importance</strong>: Despite the major implications of executive deficits in day-to-day functioning, few studies have investigated this in post-acute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection using standardized measures that differentiate between aspects of executive function.</p> <p><strong>Objective</strong>: Examine whether SARS-CoV-2 infection is associated with deficits in executive functions and if so, investigate the duration of this association.</p> <p><strong>Design, Setting, and Participants</strong>: The present research has a cross-sectional design and uses data from the Norwegian Covid-19 Cohort study. The current cohort (n = 8102) completed the Behavior Rating Inventory of Executive Function- Adult Version (BRIEF-A) electronically between April 2021 and September 2021. During the assessment, 4183 of the included participants had a prior positive polymerase chain reaction test (PCR) for SARS-CoV-2 and 3919 were untested or had a confirmed negative PCR test.</p> <p><strong>Exposure</strong>: Laboratory-confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection.</p> <p><strong>Main outcomes and measures</strong>: Executive functions were measured using the BRIEF-A, a self-report questionnaire comprising 75 items within nine theoretically and empirically distinct clinical scales. All participants self-reported on demographical variables and comorbidity. Information on sex and age was derived from the personal identification number, and vaccination status was obtained from the Norwegian Immunization Registry (SYSVAK).</p> <p><strong>Results</strong>: Participants with a positive SARS-CoV-2 status reported executive deficits in everyday life above the clinical threshold (T-score ≥65) more often than non-infected controls (383 vs. 225). Specifically, the SARS-CoV-2 positive status group indicated significantly more deficits related to metacognition, with the greatest difference demonstrated for working memory. This difference remained when adjusting for various demographic factors and comorbidities, with significantly greater odds of reporting above the clinical threshold following SARS-CoV-2 infection, as observed on the global executive composite score 6–12 months after infection (OR 1.97; 95% CI 1.51 to 2.55).</p> <p><strong>Conclusions</strong>: Our study confirms more perceived executive deficits following SARS-CoV-2 infection compared to non-infected controls, with metacognitive aspects being the most affected. These findings shed light on the potential functional difficulties that individuals may encounter during the post-acute phase of SARS-CoV-2 infection and may guide further development of targeted interventions addressing metacognitive domains of executive functioning.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news"/><category term="publication"/><category term="publication"/><category term="bbi-health"/><category term="ncc"/><category term="covid19"/><category term="cognition"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cognitive deficits after SARS-CoV-2 infection published in Brain, Behavior, & Immunity - Health]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">News – Correspondence published in The Lancet</title><link href="https://annyg.github.io/blog/2024/publication_lancet_correspondence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="News – Correspondence published in The Lancet"/><published>2024-04-06T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-06T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annyg.github.io/blog/2024/publication_lancet_correspondence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annyg.github.io/blog/2024/publication_lancet_correspondence/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="news">News</h3> <p>I am proud to share that The Lancet have published our <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(24)00414-8/fulltext">correspondence</a> regarding the retraction of an influential <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(20)32656-8/fulltext">long-COVID publication</a> that was published in The Lancet in 2021.</p> <p>The retraction of the publication was based on the discovery of data inconcistencies in the study, which we brought to the attention of the editors of The Lancet. More specifically, we highlighted inconcistencies between data from the now retracted (and republished) <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(20)32656-8/fulltext">6-month followup publication</a> and the subsequent <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(21)01755-4/fulltext">12-month followup publication</a> which also relied on data from the 6-month followup.</p> <p>After we reached out to The Lancet, an initial <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(22)02370-4/fulltext">expression of concern</a> was published by The Lancet, until the the original 6-month publication was later retracted.</p> <p>We are happy to see that the 6-month followup publication has been retracted and published in a corrected form, and that the authors have addressed some of our concerns. However, we still have some concerns that have not been addressed, and we therefore feel that it is important to publish our correspondence to ensure that these concers are brought forward to the wider scientific community.</p> <p>Briefly, when we reached out to The Lancet we also highlighted some methodological concerns, in addition to the data inconcistencies, that we felt should be addressed. We highlighted that there were differences in the phrasing of the questionnaires used at the 6-month followup and the 12-month followup. These questions were foundational for the conclusions reached in the 12-month followup publication. This difference likely hampers the conclusion that is presented in the 12-month paper that <em>“Most COVID-19 survivors had a good physical and functional recovery during 1-year follow-up, and had returned to their original work and life.”</em>, and we believe that the conclusion of the 12-month paper should be revised to reflect the data inconsistencies and methodological inconcistencies that have been brought to light.</p> <p>The retraction of this paper has also been covered by the scientific integrity blog <a href="https://retractionwatch.com/">Retraction Watch</a>, which tracks retractions and other scientific integrity issues. The blog has coverd this story from the initial <a href="https://retractionwatch.com/2022/12/01/buzzy-lancet-long-covid-paper-under-investigation-for-data-errors/">expression of concern</a> to the <a href="https://retractionwatch.com/2023/06/13/highly-cited-lancet-long-covid-study-retracted-and-republished/">retraction and republishing</a> of the paper. This retraction is also included in the list of <a href="https://retractionwatch.com/retracted-coronavirus-covid-19-papers/">Retracted coronavirus (COVID-19) papers</a>.</p> <p>We hope that our correspondence will serve as a reminder to all researchers to adhere to the highest standards of scientific integrity and to ensure that their work is conducted in an ethical manner. We also hope that it will encourage journals to implement more rigorous quality control measures to prevent similar incidents from occurring in the future.</p> <p>We would like to thank The Lancet for their transparency in this matter, and for their willingness to publish our correspondence. We would also like to thank the authors of the original publication for their cooperation in addressing our concerns.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news"/><category term="publication"/><category term="publication"/><category term="lancet"/><category term="ncc"/><category term="covid19"/><category term="retraction"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Correspondence regarding retraction of influential long-COVID publication published in The Lancet]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">INS NYC 2024 Conference</title><link href="https://annyg.github.io/blog/2024/conference_ins_nyc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="INS NYC 2024 Conference"/><published>2024-02-19T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-19T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annyg.github.io/blog/2024/conference_ins_nyc</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annyg.github.io/blog/2024/conference_ins_nyc/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="my-experience-at-the-ins-nyc-2024-conference">My Experience at the INS NYC 2024 Conference</h3> <p>Last week, I had the opportunity to attend the <a href="https://the-ins.org/meetings/new-york-2024/">52nd Annual North American Meeting of the International Neuropsychological Society (INS) in New York City</a>. It was a four-day event that brought together researchers, clinicians, and students from around the world to share their latest findings and insights on various topics related to neuropsychology.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/welcome-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/welcome-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/welcome-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/welcome.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/times_square2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/times_square2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/times_square2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/times_square2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/brooklyn-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/brooklyn-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/brooklyn-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/brooklyn.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The conference program was packed with interesting and informative sessions, ranging from keynote lectures and symposia to poster presentations and workshops. The topics covered a wide range of areas, including the neuropsychology of aging, neurodevelopmental disorders, traumatic brain injury, and neurodegenerative diseases. There were also several sessions focused on the impact of COVID-19 on the brain and cognition.</p> <p>As a member of the <a href="https://the-ins.org/sigs/">NeuroCOVID-19 special interest group</a>, I was also particularly interested in topics related to COVID-19 and its impact on the brain and cognition. The special interest group had a designated workshop session where we discussed the the current state of COVID-19 research, and discussed the future of neuropsychological sequelae of COVID-19, the challenges of assessing and treating patients with long COVID, and the potential mechanisms of neuroinvasion and neuroinflammation caused by the virus. We also had the chance to present a poster on the topic of executive dysfunction after COVID-19, which received positive feedback and sparked interesting discussions with other attendees.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/poster_session-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/poster_session-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/poster_session-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/poster_session.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/poster-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/poster-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/poster-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/poster.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/paper_session-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/paper_session-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/paper_session-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/paper_session.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>I also enjoyed networking with other attendees and exchanging ideas and experiences. I met some of the leading experts in the field, as well as some of the emerging talents. I learned a lot from their feedback and suggestions, and I hope to collaborate with some of them in the future.</p> <p>In addition to attending the conference, I also had a great time visiting New York and Manhattan. The conference center was conveniently situated in the middle of Times Square, and in the off time I got to explore the city in the February weather and visit several of the iconic landmarks. I also had the chance to try some delicious bucket-list foods.</p> <p>Overall, the INS NYC 2024 conference was a rewarding and stimulating experience for me. I gained new knowledge, expanded my professional network, and had fun exploring the city. I would highly recommend future INS meetings for those who find topics related to neuropsychology and cognition interesting.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="conference"/><category term="conference"/><category term="travel"/><category term="covid19"/><category term="ncc"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Experiences at the INS NYC 2024 Conference]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">News – Publication in The BMJ</title><link href="https://annyg.github.io/blog/2022/publication_bmj_cloc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="News – Publication in The BMJ"/><published>2022-09-07T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-07T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annyg.github.io/blog/2022/publication_bmj_cloc</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annyg.github.io/blog/2022/publication_bmj_cloc/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="news">News</h3> <p>I am happy to announce that our study investigating whether D-vitamin and cod liver oil supplementation can prevent SARS-CoV-2 infection, serious covid-19, or other acute respiratory infections in adults in Norway has been published.</p> <p>The study is published in <a href="https://www.bmj.com/content/378/bmj-2022-071245.long">The BMJ</a>.</p> <h4 id="abstract">Abstract</h4> <p>Objective: To determine if daily supplementation with cod liver oil, a low dose vitamin D supplement, in winter, prevents SARS-CoV-2 infection, serious covid-19, or other acute respiratory infections in adults in Norway.</p> <p>Design: Quadruple blinded, randomised placebo controlled trial.</p> <p>Setting: Norway, 10 November 2020 to 2 June 2021.</p> <p>Participants: 34 601 adults (aged 18-75 years), not taking daily vitamin D supplements.</p> <p>Intervention: 5 mL/day of cod liver oil (10 µg of vitamin D, n=17 278) or placebo (n=17 323) for up to six months.</p> <p>Main outcome measures: Four co-primary endpoints were predefined: the first was a positive SARS-CoV-2 test result determined by reverse transcriptase-quantitative polymerase chain reaction and the second was serious covid-19, defined as self-reported dyspnoea, admission to hospital, or death. Other acute respiratory infections were indicated by the third and fourth co-primary endpoints: a negative SARS-CoV-2 test result and self-reported symptoms. Side effects related to the supplementation were self-reported. The fallback method was used to handle multiple comparisons.</p> <p>Results: Supplementation with cod liver oil was not associated with a reduced risk of any of the co-primary endpoints. Participants took the supplement (cod liver oil or placebo) for a median of 164 days, and 227 (1.31%) participants in the cod liver oil group and 228 (1.32%) participants in the placebo group had a positive SARS-CoV-2 test result (relative risk 1.00, multiple comparison adjusted confidence interval 0.82 to 1.22). Serious covid-19 was identified in 121 (0.70%) participants in the cod liver oil group and in 101 (0.58%) participants in the placebo group (1.20, 0.87 to 1.65). 8546 (49.46%) and 8565 (49.44%) participants in the cod liver oil and placebo groups, respectively, had ≥1 negative SARS-CoV-2 test results (1.00, 0.97 to 1.04). 3964 (22.94%) and 3834 (22.13%) participants in the cod liver oil and placebo groups, respectively, reported ≥1 acute respiratory infections (1.04, 0.97 to 1.11). Only low grade side effects were reported in the cod liver oil and placebo groups.</p> <p>Conclusion: Supplementation with cod liver oil in the winter did not reduce the incidence of SARS-CoV-2 infection, serious covid-19, or other acute respiratory infections compared with placebo.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news"/><category term="publication"/><category term="publication"/><category term="bmj"/><category term="ncc"/><category term="cloc"/><category term="covid19"/><category term="vitaminD"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cod liver oil for prevention of COVID-19 (CLOC-study) published in The BMJ]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scientific Reports paper in Top 100 collection</title><link href="https://annyg.github.io/blog/2021/scirep_nano_top100/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scientific Reports paper in Top 100 collection"/><published>2021-03-31T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-31T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annyg.github.io/blog/2021/scirep_nano_top100</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annyg.github.io/blog/2021/scirep_nano_top100/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="news">News</h3> <p>I am very excited to share that happy to announce that our study published in <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-020-59771-0">Scientific Reports</a> investigating the potential of Nanopore MinION and Illumina MiSeq 16S rRNA gene sequencing to characterize building-dust microbiomes is one of the most downloaded microbiology papers published in Scientific Reports in 2020.</p> <p>The paper has been added to the <a href="https://www.nature.com/collections/hjjcbjfhhc"><strong>Top 100 in Microbiology</strong></a> collection, which showcases the top 100 most downloaded microbiology papers published in Scientific Reports in 2020.</p> <p>This study was part of my PhD project and I am very happy to see it being recognized and downloaded by the scientific community.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news"/><category term="publication"/><category term="publication"/><category term="scirep"/><category term="phd"/><category term="microbiome"/><category term="award"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Scientific Reports paper in Top 100 collection for 2020]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">News – Publication in Scientific Reports</title><link href="https://annyg.github.io/blog/2020/publication_scirep_nano/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="News – Publication in Scientific Reports"/><published>2020-03-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annyg.github.io/blog/2020/publication_scirep_nano</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annyg.github.io/blog/2020/publication_scirep_nano/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="news">News</h3> <p>I am happy to announce that our study investigating the potential of Nanopore MinION and Illumina MiSeq 16S rRNA gene sequencing to characterize building-dust microbiomes has been published.</p> <p>The study is published in <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-020-59771-0">Scientific Reports</a>.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/publication_preview/scirep_nano-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/publication_preview/scirep_nano-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/publication_preview/scirep_nano-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/publication_preview/scirep_nano.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure from the paper showing the correlation of identified taxa at different taxonomic levels. </div> <h4 id="abstract">Abstract</h4> <p>There is a growing awareness of the importance of indoor microbiomes for human health. Given their complexity, these microbiomes can only be adequately surveyed using high throughput sequencing techniques. Oxford Nanopore’s MinION is the newest third generation sequencing technology on the market. With its many advantages such as portability, user friendliness, simplicity, speed of sequencing and long read length, the technology is now an actual contender to established sequencing platforms. MinION’s main disadvantage is a relatively low read accuracy compared to several other platforms, although this is constantly improving. The present study, which appears to be the first of its kind, provides the results of a preliminary analysis of the microbial communities in indoor environments based on 16S rRNA gene amplicon sequencing, using both the Oxford Nanopore Technologies (ONT) MinIOn and the Illumina MiSeq DNA sequencers. At the level of family and above, there was no significant difference between the microbial compositions as revealed by the two platforms. However, at the genus, and particularly at the species level, the ONT MinION reported greater taxonomic resolution than Illumina MiSeq.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news"/><category term="publication"/><category term="publication"/><category term="scirep"/><category term="phd"/><category term="microbiome"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[16S sequencing using Nanopore and Illumina published in Scientific Reports]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">News – Publication in Microbiome</title><link href="https://annyg.github.io/blog/2018/publication_microbiome_long/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="News – Publication in Microbiome"/><published>2018-03-02T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-03-02T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annyg.github.io/blog/2018/publication_microbiome_long</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annyg.github.io/blog/2018/publication_microbiome_long/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="news">News</h3> <p>I am happy to announce that our study investigating the potential of Nanopore MinION and Illumina MiSeq 16S rRNA gene sequencing to characterize building-dust microbiomes has been published.</p> <p>The study is published in <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-020-59771-0">Scientific Reports</a>.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/publication_preview/scirep_nano-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/publication_preview/scirep_nano-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/publication_preview/scirep_nano-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/publication_preview/scirep_nano.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure from the paper showing the correlation of identified taxa at different taxonomic levels. </div> <h4 id="abstract">Abstract</h4> <p>There is a growing awareness of the importance of indoor microbiomes for human health. Given their complexity, these microbiomes can only be adequately surveyed using high throughput sequencing techniques. Oxford Nanopore’s MinION is the newest third generation sequencing technology on the market. With its many advantages such as portability, user friendliness, simplicity, speed of sequencing and long read length, the technology is now an actual contender to established sequencing platforms. MinION’s main disadvantage is a relatively low read accuracy compared to several other platforms, although this is constantly improving. The present study, which appears to be the first of its kind, provides the results of a preliminary analysis of the microbial communities in indoor environments based on 16S rRNA gene amplicon sequencing, using both the Oxford Nanopore Technologies (ONT) MinIOn and the Illumina MiSeq DNA sequencers. At the level of family and above, there was no significant difference between the microbial compositions as revealed by the two platforms. However, at the genus, and particularly at the species level, the ONT MinION reported greater taxonomic resolution than Illumina MiSeq.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="news"/><category term="publication"/><category term="publication"/><category term="scirep"/><category term="phd"/><category term="microbiome"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[16S sequencing using Nanopore and Illumina published in Scientific Reports]]></summary></entry></feed>